<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The death of King Charles I proved a down-right murder, with the aggravations of it in a sermon at St. Botolph Aldgate, London, January 30, 1692/3 : to which are added, some just reflections upon some late papers, concerning that King's book / by Rich. Hollingworth.</title>
            <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13678</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12539888</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12539888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 670:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The death of King Charles I proved a down-right murder, with the aggravations of it in a sermon at St. Botolph Aldgate, London, January 30, 1692/3 : to which are added, some just reflections upon some late papers, concerning that King's book / by Rich. Hollingworth.</title>
                  <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Norton for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Eikon basilike.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:1"/>
            <p>THE DEATH OF King Charles I. Proved a Down-right MURDER, With the Aggravations of it. IN A SERMON AT St. <hi>Botolph Aldgate,</hi> LONDON, <hi>January</hi> 30. 1692/3. To which are Added, ſome Juſt Reflections upon ſome late Papers, concerning That King's Book.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICH. HOLLINGWORTH,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Norton</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1693.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:2"/>
            <head>To the INHABITANTS Of St. <hi>Botolph Aldgate, LONDON,</hi> Who are true Lovers of Old <hi>England</hi> indeed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My good Friends and Pariſhioners,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is a certain bold Libeller, who has been pleaſed under the Name of <hi>Ludlow</hi> a Regicide, to load me with a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reproaches and falſe Stories in ſeveral lewd Pamphlets, in order to prejudice you againſt my Perſon, and thereby to hinder the ſucceſs of my Miniſtry amongſt you; which, thanks be to God, has had very little effect as yet, and I hope ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will: for I muſt ſay thus much, that I have found the Love and Reſpects of abundance of You rather encreaſe than diminiſh, ever ſince I undertook the honeſt and juſt Defence of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt into my hands; but however that You may not repent of ſtanding by me in this good Cauſe, I think it very neceſſary to take this
<pb facs="tcp:62945:3"/>occaſion to defend my ſelf againſt an Imputation of this bad Man's, to wit, of Forgery, a Sin of which if I thought, or knew my ſelf guilty, I ſhould Bluſh, nay Tremble, ever to come into a Pulpit, to Preach the Doctrines of the Goſpel either to You, or any other perſons whatſoever; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I ſhall with all freedom and unreſervedneſs let You into the Knowledge of this thing, which he calls Forgery.</p>
            <p>Being the laſt Summer at my Lord Biſhop of <hi>London's,</hi> I accidentally met with the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mr. <hi>Lamplugh</hi> Son to the late Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>York,</hi> who was pleaſed, knowing that I was engaged in the Cauſe of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, to ſhew me Mr. <hi>Henderſon's</hi> Death-bed Declaration, which he found in his Father's ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and upon my requeſt, to lend it me, which after I had read, and found ſo very Honeſt, ſo plain and hearty a Character, and ſo agreeable to what by an uninterrupted Tradition had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered down to us of this Age, both by <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotchmen,</hi> namely, that Mr. <hi>Henderſon</hi> after a thorow acquaintance and converſation with King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way perfectly changed as to his Opinion of that King's Sanctity, Learning and profound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and with great grief that he had been
<pb facs="tcp:62945:3"/>inſtrumental to the Miſeries that Good Man was brought to, at that time: I ſay, it being ſo agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what was ſo generally ſaid of Mr. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon,</hi> I, after I had ſhewed it to many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of great Character and Conſideration in Our Church, and by them encouraged to make it more publick reſolved to Re-print it, that the World might ſee how much that Great and Good Man was abuſed by this Libeller, who ſo impudently brands him with the Name of <hi>Nimrod, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> and unaccountable Tyrant, which Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, as it wonderfully pleaſed all that wiſh well to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy; ſo it had the contrary effect upon our Commonwealths men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in half a Years time this Scribler makes a ſhift to get Two pretended Papers to Prove this a Forgery: The Firſt is, as he tells you, a Letter from a grave and worthy Gentleman who lived in <hi>Scotland</hi> about that time, and was very conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in the great Affairs of that Kingdom: And what ſays this grave and knowing Gentleman to this affair? why he tells him, he never heard of this Declaration neither there nor here, and that had it been true, to wit, that there was ſuch a one, the World would have been full of it. Strange, that this Man ſo converſant in the great Affairs of <hi>Scotland</hi> at that time, ſhould not hear of a
<pb facs="tcp:62945:4"/>Declaration of the General Aſſembly, as to the Falſhood and Forgery of that Book; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this very thing muſt make any Man, not prejudiced, call in queſtion the Truth of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies Declaration, eſpecially conſidering this bold Man puts it out, without any atteſtation from any Publick Notary, or any other Creditable Witneſſes, whom he might have employed to ſearch the Records, and therefore I believe upon this account the World will lay the Forgery at his Door, and not at mine; eſpecially when I tell him this Story, that I have from a great and undoubted hand: That Mr. <hi>Henderſon</hi> when he came from <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> did deſign to unboſome himſelf in the great Church at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as to the Vertues of that great King, and the Reaſons of the Change of his Opinion of Him; which was underſtood by ſome great Leaders in the Aſſembly, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they hindred his Preaching; after which he fell Sick and Dyed, and no doubt to unburthen and eaſe his Mind, drew up in this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what he intended to Preach, had he been permitted. And now, I think, my Good Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, You will ſay I have ſufficiently defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my ſelf from the baſe Imputation of a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerer.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:4"/>
            <p>The other things I ſhall trouble you with the account of, are ſome Papers ſaid lately to be found, which plainly, as they ſay, make it out that King <hi>Charles I.</hi> was not the Author of that Book, which for forty odd Years has gone in his Name. Theſe Papers, by the kindneſs of the Gentleman in whoſe hands they are, I have exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined twice, and I am very ſorry, for Dr. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>'s Memory ſake, that they have been ſo much expoſed, becauſe in my Remarks upon them, ſome things muſt fall very hard upon that Prelate, which I ſhould be very averſe to, was not the Name, Honour, Religion and Learning of King <hi>Charles</hi> concerned, which, I hope, will excuſe me amongſt all Men that underſtand the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Perſons, eſpecially of a King and a Subject.</p>
            <p>The firſt Paper I ſhall take notice of, is a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the King for the Biſhoprick of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> which, indeed, for his Memory's ſake, ought by no means to have been expoſed to view; it is ſo Romantick, ſo childiſhly cracking and boaſting of his Heroick and Secret Service, that a Man would think the poor Man had utterly forgot and loſt all the impreſſions of common Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy and Prudence, and was reſolved to provoke the King to command him out of <hi>White-Hall;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62945:5"/>as a Man not fit to be a Countrey Curate, much leſs preferred to the wealthieſt Biſhoprick in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> But the beſt of it is, though he had the vanity to draw it up, he was yet ſo wiſe as not to preſent it, which is plain from his own mouth; for Page <hi>5</hi> of Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> we have this Story, That the laſt time Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> ſaw him, which was after he was Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, he asked him whether King <hi>Charles II.</hi> knew that he wrote the Book? He gave him this anſwer; That I cannot poſitively and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſay he doth, becauſe he was never pleaſed to take expreſs notice of it to me: The truth of it is, when I conſider that Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> ſays, That Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> took the Covenant; and that when Mr. <hi>Zach. Crofton</hi> charges Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> as one of the number of Covenanters: And Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> denies all, Page <hi>275.</hi> of <hi>Anti-Baal,</hi> and ſays, That Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> reckons without his Hoſt, when he made him one of the number of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters, and poſitively aſſures the World, that he never took any Oaths but thoſe appointed by Law, no League nor Vow, and that if he had done it, he muſt have had no peace 'till he had publickly repented, and recanted ſuch Diſſimulation, which he abhors as Hell. I ſay, when I read this, I wonder at, nay, I believe, nothing that Dr. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62945:5"/>either ſaid or did, in order to get a fat Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick: but before I leave this Paper, give me leave to ſay, that the Style is ſo like to all his other Writings, and ſo altogether unlike the King's Book, that I will as ſoon believe that Mr. <hi>Ralph Venning,</hi> who Writ two Books, called <hi>Milk and Honey,</hi> and <hi>Orthodox Paradoxes,</hi> or that Mr. <hi>William Seckar,</hi> who Writ the fulſom Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, called the <hi>Wedding Ring,</hi> could have Writ the <hi>Whole Duty of Man,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Saints Everlaſting Reſt,</hi> as that Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> could Write the <hi>Eicon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Paper is a Letter to my Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour <hi>Hide,</hi> ſtill for the Biſhoprick of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter:</hi> And the Truth of it is, here he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plays himſelf to the full, and ſhews his Virtues all at once; and how far the World ought to give credit to his pretences, for he down-right offers to commit the ſin of Simony, and bids one half of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> to get the other; a fit Man indeed, to Write ſuch Holy and Divine Meditations as are contained in the King's Book; who rather than miſs his Ambitious Aims, will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the door of Perjury, and, I am ſure he that will forſwear himſelf, will not fail to tell a falſehood, when Covetouſneſs and Pride have the Aſcendant of him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:6"/>
            <p>The next and laſt Paper I ſhall take notice of, is a long Narrative of Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s, all which depends upon her Husband's Truth, and which will not hold together when it comes ſtrictly to be examined. She tells you of an intercourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second and Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> about the Book, and the King upon ſatisfaction that he wrote it, promiſed him the Reverſion of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Wincheſter;</hi> and yet as by the former Story appears, the King, even after he was Elect of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> never ſaid word to him of any ſuch thing. She further poſitively aſſerts, that her Husband ſent the Manuſcript to the King at the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> and that the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, and ſent Biſhop <hi>Duppa</hi> to give Dr. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> an account of it: and yet, <hi>pag. 5.</hi> of Dr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> he asking Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> whether the King had ever ſeen the Book, he gave him this Anſwer, I know it certainly no more than you; but I uſed my beſt endeavours that he might, for I delivered a Copy of it to the Marqueſs of <hi>Hartford,</hi> when he went to the Treaty at the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> and intreated his Lordſhip, if he could obtain any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate opportunity he would deliver it to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and humbly deſire to know his Majeſty's pleaſure concerning it. But the Violence which threatned the King, haſtning ſo faſt, he ventured
<pb facs="tcp:62945:6"/>to Print it, and never knew what was the iſſue of ſending it. Here is brave work, my Maſters, Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> down-right giving Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi> the lye. She tells you in another place, that it was ſome few days after the King's Murder, that her Husband got the Book, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it: whereas it is well known, the Book was Printed off before the King's Murder.</p>
            <p>But commend me to the laſt poſitive aſſertion of this Lady, for ſhe tells you, that ſome of the Rump-Parliaments Friends took the very Manuſcript her Husband ſent to his Majeſty, and appointed a private Committee, to find out the buſineſs. This had been brave for Mr. <hi>Milton,</hi> and I am ſure we ſhould have heard of it again and again, in his Anſwer to the King's Book; and no doubt that Remnant of the Houſe that ſat and were ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at this Book, and loſt ſo much ground through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kingdom, by Vertue of this Book, would have ſent this news all over the Nation: but not one word of all this, but the Book paſſed, as it ought to do, for above <hi>12.</hi> Years together, as the King's own. And ſo I take my leave of Mrs. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> but not without expreſſing my hearty ſorrow, that I am abſolutely neceſſitated to theſe Remarks and Reflections upon Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> and his Wife; for I take no pleaſure neither in ſpeaking ill of,
<pb facs="tcp:62945:7"/>nor doing ill to any Man or Woman whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome will ſay, pray why did my Lord Chancellour <hi>Hide</hi> ſeem to believe it: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that he was perfectly impoſed upon, by Dr. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and knew nothing of the matter it ſelf; for he never ſaw the King's face after he left <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> being always excepted out of Pardon by the Parliament, and ſo became wholly a ſtranger to the King's private Tranſactions.</p>
            <p>And now, my good Friends and Neighbours, I ſhall only trouble you, by asking you whether thoſe are not very credulous Men, and have Throats that will ſwallow Mountains, that make theſe vain contradictory Papers weigh down the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Major <hi>Huntington;</hi> who after <hi>Nazeby</hi> fight, procured ſo much of the King's Book as was then drawn up from <hi>Fairfax</hi> the General, and delivered the Papers with his own hand to the King, who received them with great joy, and told him, that he eſteemed them more than all the Jewels he had loſt in his Cabinet, which was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted to me by Mr. <hi>Cave Becke,</hi> a Reverend, Pious and Learned Miniſter, now living in <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwich,</hi> from the mouth of the Major, in a Letter under his own hand: and alſo by Mr. <hi>Ric. Duke</hi> of <hi>Devon,</hi> and ſeveral others in the ſame County to <hi>Mr. Read,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Barnſtaple,</hi> who all
<pb facs="tcp:62945:7"/>had it from the Major himſelf; or will weigh down the Evidence of that holy, humble, modeſt and admirable learned Man Dr. <hi>Dillingham,</hi> ſometimes Fellow and Maſter of <hi>Emanuel</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> who declared to his Son, which I have formerly Printed from a Letter writ by himſelf to a Reverend Miniſter in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> That his Father read in the King's Cloſet at <hi>Holdenby,</hi> preſently after he came from <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> ſeveral Sentences newly writ, as he ſuppoſed, by the King's own hand, which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards found exactly in a Chapter of the King's Book; the Truth of which Story has been very lately confirmed to me by the Reverend Mr. <hi>Saunderſon,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>Emanuel</hi> College, to whom that learned Doctor did tell it more than once: Or, further, Whether theſe vain and unaccountable Papers will weigh down the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Sir <hi>John Brattle,</hi> lately deceaſed, who has declared a hundred and a hundred times, within this laſt year, to my ſelf and others, That he aſſiſted his Father in methodizing the King's looſe Papers, which made up the greateſt part of this Book in the Year <hi>1647.</hi> and which were brought to his Father by the King's Order, by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Juxon</hi> for that purpoſe; or weigh down the credit of that holy, honeſt and couragious Sufferer
<pb facs="tcp:62945:8"/>Mr. <hi>Simmonds:</hi> All which Characters will appear in a few Weeks to be true of him, by his Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Vindication of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt,</hi> which was Printed in <hi>48.</hi> and now Re-printed again by my ſelf, who all along in his Sickneſs, and to his laſt Breath, declared it to be the King's own Book, and none others, whoſe only fault was in the truſt repoſed in him by the King to Print and Correct this Book, that he ſhowed it to Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> and let him too much into the knowledge of it, who thereupon, Mr. <hi>Simmonds</hi> being dead, and the Marqueſs of <hi>Worceſter</hi> too, who, if living, could have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, to his ſhame, all his Pretences, in order to ſerve his ambitious ends, ſets up for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Book. Or laſtly, weigh down the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> who ſo ſacredly has declared, that he heard Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> declare, and often affirm, that he was fully convinced, that the Book was entirely that King's Work. I now, my good Friends, appeal to you all, to judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe ſo much cryed-up Papers, and the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt them for that great and good King; and I leave my ſelf in your hands, and the hands of all the diſ-intereſted and unprejudiced part of the Kingdom, to judge whether I am guilty of Forgery, that great ſin a late Barbarous Libeller lays to my charge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:8"/>
            <p>I ſhall detain you no longer than to tell you, That the reaſon of my Zeal and Labour in the Vindication of this King, next to my ſatisfaction in his Perſonal Vertues, it, that the Principles by which this King was Murdered, and by which his Murder is now juſtified, will, if they prevail once more, deſtroy our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ancient Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and tear up by the Roots again, the beſt conſtituted Church in the World; and by the Grace of God, as I will never contribute to ſuch a Deſign, ſo according to my ſmall Ability, I will in my place endeavour to prevent it, let what will come of Me and Mine. My good Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, praying for your Health and Happineſs, and thanking of you for your continued kindneſs to me, I am your hearty loving Friend and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICH. HOLLINGWORTH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:9"/>
            <head>TO THE Counterfeit LUDLOW.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas you challenge me as to the Truth of the Story concerning Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi> to a Lady, if you pleaſe to come, or ſend to me, I will direct you to that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Perſon, who will ſatisfie you, that a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy told him above ſixteen years ago, that Mrs. <hi>Gauden</hi> told her, That ſhe queſtioned the Eternal State of her Husband, becauſe he pretended to be the Author of a Book, which to her knowledge he never wrote. And when you know him, you will ſay I am not out, when I ſay, He is as conſiderable a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as moſt that wears a Gown.</p>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guil. Lancaſter.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62945:9"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YEſterday, being the <hi>15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>February,</hi> a very Worthy and particular Friend of mine, was pleaſed to come to my houſe, and to inform me, That one Captain <hi>Rhodes,</hi> together with his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, could give me a farther account of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's Book; upon which I gave the ſaid Captain a meeting the laſt Night, who was pleaſed to invite me to his Houſe this afternoon, being the <hi>16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> inſtant, where and when the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a grave, ſerious Gentlewoman, did declare to me, that her Husband Dr. <hi>Rhodes,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Haughton</hi> and <hi>Thorpe</hi> near <hi>Newark,</hi> did live in <hi>Newark</hi> in the time it was a Gariſon, while the King was there, and that the King came often to her Houſe, to diſcourſe with her Husband, and that her Husband did conduct the King in a diſguiſe, from <hi>Newark</hi> to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and was with him often, from that time till his being a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> where he attended him alſo; in all which places he ſaw thoſe parts of the King's Book which he then drew up, Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:62945:10"/>with his own hand, being ſo intimate with the King, and ſo intirely beloved by him, as to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into his Cloſets and ſecret Communications: all which her Husband often told her as great Truths; and the ſaid Captain, her Son, did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to me, which he will when lawfully called reſtifie upon Oath, that he was in company with Sir <hi>Francis Leake,</hi> and one Major <hi>Millington</hi> a Sectary, and his Father, when a diſcourſe ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing about this Book, his Father ſolemnly laid his Hand upon his Breaſt and ſaid, upon the Word of an Honeſt Man, I have at ſeveral times, and in ſeveral places, ſeen and read theſe Papers, Writ with the King's own hand. This Captain <hi>Rhodes</hi> and his Mother live in <hi>Manſel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Goodman's Fields,</hi> within two doors of the <hi>Green Man,</hi> and will juſtifie the Truth of what I have ſaid, to any that have the curioſity to ask them. And now, Mr. <hi>Ben. Hatley,</hi> who againſt Faith and Promiſe, expoſed theſe falſe and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Papers to publick View, at the <hi>Rummer</hi> in <hi>Queen-ſtreet,</hi> and ſuffered a ſilly abſtract to be taken by the Counterfeit <hi>Ludlow:</hi> much good may your Deſign do you, though I aſſure you Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s Relations have no reaſon to thank you.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62945:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MATTHEW XIX. 18.</hi> Jeſus ſaid, Thou ſhalt do no Murder.</head>
            <p>WHEN God Created Man, He deſigned that his Iſſue and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity ſhould live in Love and Peace with one another, mutually Helping and Aſſiſting each other, according to their ſeveral Neceſſities and Straits: and therefore, when <hi>Cain</hi> roſe up againſt his Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> and embrued his Hands in his Bloud, the great God, to ſhew his abhorrence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the Sin, tells him, that the Voice of his Brother's Bloud, was come to Him from the ground; and in Judgment makes him a Vagabond and a Wanderer, and afterwards makes a ſtanding Law in order to deterr Men from a Sin, that did ſo break in upon the Reaſon of his Creation, and the Laws of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; <hi>That whoſoever did ſhed</hi> Man's Bloud,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62945:11"/>by Man ſhould his Bloud be ſhed. And when He gave the Ten Commandments by the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> He inſerted this for one, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>That he ſhould not kill.</hi> And our Saviour who came to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil all Righteouſneſs, and as He tells us him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Not to deſtroy, but to fulfil the Law,</hi> namely, To ſet things in a clearer Light, to found the Practice of them upon Nobler Principles, to carry them to Nobler Ends, and to give Men greater Spiritual Aids and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances to perform them, than the <hi>Jews</hi> had under the Paedagogy of <hi>Moſes:</hi> He repeats and juſtifies this particular Law, making the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of it, one of the conditions of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, and tells the Man in the words of my Text, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Murder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of which Words, I will briefly fix the true Notion of Murder, of Killing our fellow Creatures, thoſe of the ſame Rank and Order of Being with our ſelves; and then ſee whether the Murder we are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Wiſdom of the Nation This Day to bewail, is not according to that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Murder, a real Act of Murder, and not a piece of Juſtice, as many wicked Men, at this Day, call it, and conſequently does not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62945:11"/>deſerve to be abhorred and grieved for by all Men that wiſh well to the Kingdom, and in order to it do endeavour to atone that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure which the Shedding, and the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating the ſhedding of Innocent Bloud, may juſtly raiſe in the Divine Breaſt, and which may provoke God ſtill to pour down his Judgments upon us for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>And certainly there is no good Man in the Nation but will conclude, conſidering the Circumſtances and Dangers we are in, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a powerful Enemy abroad, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo much, by ſo great deſtructive Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at home: I ſay there is no good Man but will conclude, that we ought to do all that lyes in us to procure the Bleſſings, and the kind and ſeaſonable interpoſals of Divine Providence to ſecure our Armies by Land, and our Forces by Sea, and ſo to proſper them, that we may be delivered from the hands of our Enemies, and all that hate us, our Nation and Religion. And he that by Vindicating the crying Sin of Murder, does contribute towards Divine Provocation, he is ſo far from being a Friend to the Laws and Liberties of his Countrey, that he is the greateſt Enemy they have, and ought by all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62945:12"/>Men truſted with Publick Offices either Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or Secular, to be both publickly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and with all good Temper to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved too, that ſo he may be reclaimed from a Sin that hath ſo poyſonous an influence upon the <hi>Good</hi> of the Community of which he is a Member.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, As for the True Notion of Murder, the thing forbidden in the Text; In ſhort, it is nothing elſe but the <hi>taking away</hi> another Man's Life without a Warrant from God, or Man deputed and entruſted by God, in a Judicial way to bring Men to ſuch a piece of Juſtice as deprives them <hi>of their Lives.</hi> For, it is plain from Scripture, that many Mens Lives have been taken away, by an immediate Command from God, which juſtified the Act, and took away the Notion, and conſequently the Guilt of Murder. And it is as plain, that there are many Acts of Wickedneſs that God ordered the Lawful Magiſtrate, for the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Divine Wrath and the Good of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societies to put Men to Death, which Laws have had their force in all Nations and Countries whatſoever, and indeed, without which, Humane Societies would quickly be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and the World would be like nothing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62945:12"/>but a Wilderneſs or Deſart, full of Men tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the nature of wild Bears and Tygers; and where you have one violent deſtruction of a Fellow-Creature, you would have a thouſand. So that the Murder of my Text is nothing elſe but a pretending and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking to be Maſter of another Man's Life, without any Commiſſion from God, or any Legal Tryal by Men, according to the Laws of the Country in which they live, and to which they are bound to ſubject themſelves. So that this brings me to the work and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of this day, namely, to conſider, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Death of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt was a Murder, yea, or no, or an Act of Juſtice, as ſome wicked men do ſtill pretend to call-it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here let us conſider whether they had a Commiſſion from God to do it. <hi>Now</hi> a Commiſſion from God muſt either be by a Voice from Heaven, or elſe by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of an Angel ſent by God, or ſome other way by which God did convey His Mind and Purpoſe to His People of old; none of which were ever pretended to, as the ground and reaſon of this great Man's Death, by any that had a hand in it. And therefore let us ſee what Warrant they had from the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62945:13"/>Laws of the Land. The Laws of the Land, What are they, or upon what Authority are they founded? Why, according to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, all Laws flow from the Power of King, Lords and Commons; the Lords and Commons framing and preparing Bills, ſuch as they conceive for the Good of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; and the King, by his Royal <hi>Fiat,</hi> giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life and Being to thoſe Bills, upon which they immediately become obligatory to the People of the Land: to violate or tranſgreſs which, is attended with ſuch Pains and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, as thoſe Law-makers who make up the Legiſlative Power of the Nation, think good and meet to enact; and whatſoever is offered as a Law, made without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of theſe <hi>Three Eſtates</hi> together, is an Invaſion and Encroachment upon the True and Eſſential <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: For neither the King without the Lords and Commons, nor the Lords and Commons without the King, can bind the Subject to any thing under the Notion of a Law of this Kingdom. This, my Beloved, is our happy Frame of Government, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly is the beſt the World can ſhew, and under which we ought to ſit with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62945:13"/>and pleaſure: And they that go about to ſet any of theſe Three Powers, contrary to the Law, above their places, are great Enemies to this excellent Conſtitution, and their Projects and Contrivances, their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Propoſals, have always been of very unhappy conſequence to the Kingdom in general: And for my own part, I do here profeſs my ſelf ſo great an Admirer of this happy Conſtitution, that by the Grace of God, my little Finger ſhall never be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make any jar in the Harmony and Concurrence of King, Lords and Commons; and I will always ſubmit by doing, or by ſuffering, to whatſoever they ſhall Enact: And though they ſhould paſs into a Law, what I in Conſcience could not comply with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, yet I think it my duty not to Reſiſt, but to be paſſively Obedient; which I account the true Notion of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive-Obedience;</hi> two Doctrines, which if not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and practiſed in this ſenſe I have na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, all Government is precarious, and will be in danger of being unhinged, whenever a number of diſcontented and ambitious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons get together, with Force and Strength, in order to carry on their wicked and baſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62945:14"/>deſigns, and to anſwer and gratifie their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable diſſatisfactions.</p>
            <p>Well, this being the true Notion of the Engliſh Laws, pray let us ſee whether King, Lords and Commons, ever conſented to a Law, that enabled one part to deſtroy the other, the King to deſtroy and null the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Authority of Lords and Commons; or the Lords and Commons to ſit upon, judge and take away, the Life of their King. And here I challenge the boldeſt Aſſertor of the Juſtice of the Murder of this Day, to ſhow me any one word, from the beginning of the <hi>Statute-Book</hi> to the end thereof, that looks this way, or gives ſuch a Power into any of the three parts of the Legiſlative Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Hands: And if there be no Commiſſion from the Law of the Land, then certainly this Death muſt be called, and is, a true and real Murder, the Thing forbidden in my Text. A Law to do it! No, no; they could not perpetrate this Act, before they had broke in upon the whole Frame and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Government; and they made their way to it by the moſt undutiful, rude and barbarous Acts, that Hiſtory almoſt can parallel. For at that very time when the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62945:14"/>good King had made ſuch Conceſſions as the Houſe of Commons Voted a ground for Peace: and when the tired and harraſſed Nation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <hi>their Swords to be turned into Plow-ſhares, and the Spears into pruning books,</hi> at that time did an inſolent Army, through Pride, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs and Perjury, violently aſſault their Maſters, who had ſet them on Work, and all along paid them their Wages, and ſtop'd and laid hold of many of the Members as they were going into the Houſe, and put them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a reſtraint, even to ſuch a number, that very few, conſidering of what number the Houſe ought to conſiſt, did remain behind: which Few, notwithſtanding, took upon them the Name of <hi>the People of England,</hi> and in a ſhort time, after ſome Votes, which rooted up and deſtroyed the very Fundamentals of our Government, Voted the <hi>Tryal of the King as a Traytor,</hi> and named Commiſſioners to ſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and when they ſent the Bill to the Lords for their concurrence, who nobly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected it, for ſo doing, they Voted away all the Authority of the Houſe of Lords, tho' it be by our Conſtitution the Higheſt Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature in the Kingdom. By ſuch unheard of, and Barbarous Ways, they made way for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62945:15"/>the King's <hi>Tryal,</hi> and at laſt for his inhumane Death.</p>
            <p>And now I appeal to any Man of Senſe, Reaſon or Religion, whither this was not a real Murder, and I ask with what Brow any Man that pretends a Love for his Countreys Conſtitution, can advocate and plead for ſuch an illegal Act; an Act of a few Men who took upon them an Authority our Law knows nothing of.</p>
            <p>But to put the thing out of doubt, and to ſatisfie you to the full, that this was a real Murder, I will give you an Abſtract of the Act, made by the Parliament upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, many of the Members of which, were perſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the Army, in order to the violent cutting off King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt.</p>
            <p>They declare in that Act, That <hi>The horrid and execrable Murder of our late moſt gracious Soveraign King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt, of ever-bleſſed and glorious Memory, hath been committed by a party of wretched Men, deſperately wicked and hardned in their impiety, who-having firſt plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and contrived the ruine and deſtruction of our excellent Monarchy, and with it, the True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Proteſtant Religion, which had been long
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62945:15"/>protected by it, and flouriſhed under it, to carry on their pernicious and traiterous deſigns, threw down all the Fences and Bulworks of Law, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the very Being and Conſtitution of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that they might have a way opened for any further attempt upon the Sacred Perſon of his Majeſty.</hi> Further they declare, <hi>That by many odious Acts they had fully ſtrengthened themſelves in Power and Faction—ſeiz'd upon his Royal Perſon—erected a prodigious and unheard of Tribunal, which they called an High Court of Juſtice for Tryal of his Majeſty, and at laſt with force and cruelty they brought his Sacred Majeſty to the Scaffold, and there publickly Murdered him before the Gates of his own Royal Palace. And becauſe by this horrid Action, the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath received the greateſt Wound and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and the People of</hi> England <hi>the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable Shame and Infamy that it was poſſible for the enemies of God and the King to bring upon us</hi>—Further it ſays, <hi>The Fanatick rage of a few miſcreants, who were as far from being True Proteſtants, as they were from being True Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Therefore we the Parliament do hereby renounce, abominate and proteſt againſt that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Fact, that execrable Murther, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Treaſon committed againſt the Sacred
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62945:16"/>Perſon and Life of our ſaid late Sovereign, and all proceedings thereunto. And be it hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that by the undoubted and fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, neither the Peers of this Realm, nor the Commons, nor both together in Parliament, nor the People collectively, nor repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatively, nor any other Perſon whatſoever, ever had, have or ought to have a coercive Power over the perſons of the Kings of this Realm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for the vindicating our ſelves, and as a laſting Monument to Poſterity, of our inexpreſſible deteſtation and abhorrence of this Villanous and Abominable Fact; Be it Enacted, that every</hi> 30th. of January <hi>ſhall be for over hereafter ſet a part to be kept and obſerved in all Churches and Chappels in his Majeſties Dominions as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſary day of Faſting and Humiliation to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the Mercy of God, that neither the Guilt of the Sacred and Innocent Bloud may at any time hereafter be viſited upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and our Poſterity.</hi> Then it goes on to Attaint as Traitors and Regicides, <hi>Oliver Cromwel, Edmund Ludlow, &amp;c.</hi> as notorious Wicked and Active Inſtruments in proſecuting and compaſſing that Trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Murder.</p>
            <p>And now, my Beloved, I hope, when the Wiſdom of the Nation in Parliament has
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62945:16"/>declared it ſelf ſo fully and freely, I ſay, I hope, there is none in this Congregation will deny this Fact to be a real and down-right Murder, in the ſenſe of my Text. Give me leave in the next place, to ſhow you the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations of this Murder, that ſo you may be affected with it, and thereby anſwer the Reaſon of the Day, and the deſign of thoſe that appointed it, and conſequently help to the keeping of that Divine Vengeance, which other mens juſtifying and abetting of it may juſtly pull down upon our heads. And the truth of it is, the Aggravations are great and many, and ſurmount all my little Rhetorick to make a juſt deſcription of; but however, as far as I am able, I will give you them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Conſider the Aggravation from the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that contrived and accompliſhed this horrid Murder; they were Men that had ſworn true Faith to him again and again, who had taken the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, who took the Proteſtation, by which they promiſed to defend and ſecure the King's Rights; who took the Covenant, by which they engaged at the ſame rate, and to the ſame purpoſes; Men that had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to Meſſages upon Meſſages, Petitions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62945:17"/>upon Petitions, under the Name and Notion of His Majeſty's moſt humble and dutiful Subjects; who aimed at nothing, and called God to witneſs they had nothing more in their eyes, than the ſafety, honour and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of His Majeſty's Perſon and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and yet theſe Men embrue their hands in His Bloud, and break through all the Ties and Obligations, theſe Oaths laid upon them, in order to kill and take poſſeſſion of what he had. Now certainly, my Beloved, this thing ought mightily to be bewailed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account; and God muſt needs be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with that People, who magnifie and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate not only the ſhedding of Righteous Bloud, but the working their way to it, through Perjury and Perfidiouſneſs, through Breaches upon Promiſes, reiterated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated again and again: And therefore upon this account I recommend to you weeping, and wailing, becauſe Perjury and Murder are great and crying ſins.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Another Aggravation of this Murder is the Perſon that ſuffered, and that was King <hi>Charles</hi> I. and here let us ſee whether he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſuch a barbarous death. I am very far from thinking him a man in a ſtate of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62945:17"/>Perfection; and I do acknowledge there were Errors and Failures in his Government, he came early to the Crown, and therefore might be impoſed upon; but I hope every Man does not deſerve to be knock'd o'th' Head for every particular ſlip of his life; if ſo, the beſt Kings that have Reigned would not have died natural deaths; neither <hi>David</hi> nor <hi>Solomon,</hi> neither <hi>Hezekiah</hi> nor <hi>Joſiah,</hi> nor any other Prince, recorded for vertuous and very good men.</p>
            <p>But, however, whatſoever his imperfections were in the beginning of his Reign, I am ſure before the Quarrel began with him, he rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed them all, and conſented to remove all thoſe things that were accounted grievous, and indeed filled the <hi>Statute-Book</hi> with more Privileges than it does afford now; for a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Parliament took away ſome things then eſtabliſhed, which they, in their great Wiſdom, thought neither fit for a King to grant, nor People to enjoy. The truth of it is, this Great Perſon, take him in all conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, deſerved a far better Lot than he met withal; and many of thoſe that at firſt entertained hard thoughts of him, and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt him, upon Converſation and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62945:18"/>with him, repented of what they had done; and as they ever after bore a great eſteem for him, ſo in all their diſcourſes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards repreſented him, as one of the beſt of men they ever met withal; particularly the Learned and Pious Mr. <hi>Vines,</hi> who ſaid to ſome Friends of mine, That if ever there was a <hi>Solomon</hi> ſince <hi>Solomon,</hi> it was <hi>Charles</hi> the I.</p>
            <p>And truly no wonder; for certainly he was a Man endowed with as many Vertues and Graces as moſt Princes that ever ſate upon a Throne. His Devotions in the way of the Church of <hi>England</hi> were conſtant and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; his Diſcourſes pithy and profitable; for he was a man of great Parts and admirable Improvements; his Behaviour was affable and courteous; and ſo long as he was able, poſſeſſed of his own Inheritance, he was greatly Charitable, and ready to lend his helping hand, in promoting any publick Good, which I could make out by many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; further, his Chaſtity, conſidering the Temptations he as a King might be ſuppoſed to be under, is ſcarce to be parallel'd; and his Temperance acknowledged, by all that were about him; his Patience was in ſome ſort
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62945:18"/>like that of his great Maſter's the Holy Jeſus: and tho he met with as great affronts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities, as ever Man did that wore a Crown; yet his very Enemies confeſſed that they could not throw him into a Paſſion, nor ruffle him ſo far as to break out into undecent and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Reflections; how he behaved himſelf at his Tryal, and immediately before his Death, and at the hour of Death it ſelf, pray ſearch the Hiſtory, and you will be ſatisfied, that he was acted by a more than ordinary Divine Spirit; one inſtance I cannot omit, and that is, when he was going through the Park to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Scaffold, with a Guard about him, he ſpoke to Two Perſons that did more immediately attend him, that they would go faſter, ſaying, <hi>That he now went before them to ſtrive for an Heavenly Crown, with leſs ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude than he had oftentimes bid his Souldiers to fight for an Earthly Diadem;</hi> and how he went out of the World with a clear Soul without the leaſt revenge, but praving forgiveneſs for his Enemies, you may find in the True Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the paſſages at his Death. And pray, my Beloved, what Cauſe was there now for this Great and Good Man's Murder? Yes, ſay ſome wicked Men, he was a Tyrant and a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62945:19"/>Papiſt. A Tyrant, that is ſtrange! that gave to his People all they could reaſonably ask, and frankly offered to conſent to any thing that did not ſtrip him of his Kingſhip, and that was conſiſtent with his Honour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. If ſuch a Man be a Tyrant, then You and I muſt all of us change our Notions of things, and call Good Evil, and Evil Good.</p>
            <p>And as for the Imputation of Popery, there is no Man that reads his Hiſtory with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced Mind, can believe the leaſt incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to it, if Living and Dying in perfect Communion with the moſt excellent Church in the World, if offering to do any thing that might preſerve and ſupport the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, be arguments of a Papiſt; then I muſt confeſs the Imputation is juſt: but what Man of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not a Papiſt at this rate? But thanks be to God, as he refuted this Reflection by the whole Series of his Life, and by his ſolemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation at his Death, when he was juſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give an account to God; ſo I think the Members of this Church have Preach'd, Printed and ſaid enough in the late Reign, for ever to ſilence and ſhame this Reflection and Imputation out of the World. So that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62945:19"/>hitherto we find no cauſe of Death in him at all, even if by the Laws of the Land he had been rightly tryed by a juſt Power that had as juſt an Authority to bring him to an Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Tryal: and therefore this is a great aggravation of his Death, that a Man of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and Goodneſs, a Man of Virtue and Piety, a Man indeed of a moſt Exemplary Life, ſhould be thus Butcher'd, and that by thoſe, who had no more Authority to do it, than you have to fall a cutting one anothers Throats as ſoon as this Sermon is ended. And therefore upon this ſcore, This Death ought to be bewailed, and there is great reaſon for the obſerving This Day in order to prevent the Judgments that may come upon us for ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and for the vindicating the ſhedding of this Innocent Bloud.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Another Aggravation of this Murder, is the Conſequences of it. Alas, after the Sacrifice of this great Perſon, Nobles fell by their bloudy hands, and the beſt Families were either Baniſhed or Impriſoned, and their Eſtates Confiſcated; a bloudy War with <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was commenc'd, and that free Nation brought into a perfect ſlavery, and that which was a thing of deplorable conſequence, this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62945:20"/>Good Man's Children were Baniſhed to ſeek their Bread in ſtrange Countreys, from whence proceeded the Miſeries, eſpecially of the laſt Reign: and therefore thoſe Men that flye in the face of the Two laſt Kings, ſhould do well to conſider where they were forcibly bred, and how they came to be bred there, who ſent them out of their own Countrey, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them to live upon the Bounty of Popiſh Princes: if King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt had lived out his time, they no doubt had been bred up in the ſtricteſt way in the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and no doubt would have maintained its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Honour both at home and abroad by Virtue of the Principles of their Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which muſt without all diſpute have taught them to Love and Honour, to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and Strengthen the Proteſtant Intereſt over all theſe Weſtern Parts of the World: and therefore we muſt thank theſe Murderers of this Good King, for the misfortunes of the laſt Reign, and for the Fears that are upon us at preſent.</p>
            <p>And now having proved the Murder, and ſhewed you the Aggravations of it, give me leave to ask you, whither we ought not to be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62945:20"/>ſerious in the obſervation of this Day? And whether they be not great Offenders, and bad Men, that ridicule the Day, and call it in ſcorn the <hi>madding Day?</hi> Whether they be not Men of miſchievous and provoking Principles, that ſtill continue to aſſert and juſtifie this barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Act? And whether we may not expect great Judgments to fall upon us upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count?</p>
            <p>Come therefore, my Beloved, let us all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly bethink our ſelves, and conſider what great reaſon we have to do every thing that tends to pacifie Divine Wrath at this time, and to procure His Prefence to go along with us. You all know, that we have at this time the greateſt and deareſt things that belong to us, lye at ſtake, to wit, our Religion and our Laws; we have a potent Enemy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, who yet ſcorns us, and bids defiance to all the conjoyned Forces on this ſide <hi>Europe;</hi> an Enemy, who if he prevails, will certainly bring us into the condition of his own Subjects, both as to Religion, Liberty and Property; and therefore, Oh! thou good God, give us the Interpoſals and Watchfulneſs of Thy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; lend us Thy mighty helping Hand in this our time of Trouble; let us be under Thy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62945:21"/>Conduct and Guidance, and preſerve ſtill our Noble Prince, and let him be <hi>under the ſhadow of Thy Wings, and make his Enemies to flee before him. And bleſſed are,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſays, <hi>the People that are in ſuch a caſe, and who thus have the Lord for their God.</hi> I, but my beloved, tho God is ready to help us yet he hath propoſed conditions on our part in order to an intereſt in his Power and Preſence; we muſt eſchew Evil, and do Good; we muſt forſake the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs of our ways; we muſt not ſpeak evil of Dignities, nor curſe the King, no not in our hearts, we muſt not ſhed <hi>Innocent Bloud,</hi> nor vindicate and juſtifie it when it is done. If we are reſolved upon ſuch courſes as theſe are, we muſt expect to be dealt withal by the great God accordingly; we muſt follow the example of <hi>David,</hi> and cry, <hi>Deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> us from Bloud guiltineſs, O God, thou God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Salvation,</hi> And beg that we may be warned throughly from this ſin, and cleanſed from this iniquity. I, this is the way to have ſucceſs attend our Counſels, and our Engagements both by Land and Sea. Give me leave to ſpeak plainly to you; and I hope thoſe, if there be any ſuch, as I am ſatisfied: there are, that came with a deſign to make themſelves merry here to day
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62945:21"/>with our preaching and praying, will go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with better and more ſerious Thoughts, and that becauſe the happineſs of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is concerned in their holy and pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of, and indignation againſt this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Murder. But if all this will not prevail with you, give me leave to tell theſe ſort of Men, that are reſolved to abuſe this great Martyr, and laugh at the obſervation of the Day, that at the ſame time they abuſe the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Queen,</hi> who this Day ſolemnly obſerve it; that they abuſe the Two <hi>Houſes of Parliament,</hi> who have appointed Preachers to ſet out affect them with the ſin of the Day: And withal let me tell you, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their profeſſions of Honour to, and kindneſs for King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> yet they are unmannerly and clowniſh, ill bred and rude perſons; for if King <hi>Charles</hi> I had had no perſonal Vertues to recommend him to the World, yet methinks they ſhould be ſo civil, and ſo far make good their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions of Honour and Affection to K. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> as at leaſt to hold their Tongues, and keep them from railing againſt him, and that barely becauſe he was the King and Queen's Grandfather.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62945:22"/>
            <p>And now tho' I have ſaid ſo much as I am ſure will convince all good men, yet I am ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied there are a Generation of Men will not ceaſe to vent their rage againſt this great Prince, and in order to it have very lately cryed up, and triumphed in a diſcovery of ſome Papers, which ſeem to rob him of the glory and honour of being Author of his excellent Book: which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers I have read, and find them Romantick and vain-glorious, making a ſimoniacal offer, in order to obtain the beſt Biſhoprick in <hi>England,</hi> and withal ſo contradictory to plain evidence two years before they are pretended to be writ by the Author, and ſo vaſtly different from the noble Air, and Stile, and Spirit of that excellent Book, that I do here in the face of this Congregation, challenge the Party to Print the Papers, and do aſſure them they ſhall have a juſt Examination and Conſideration in a due and convenient time; and this great King's Memory will ſtill be preſerved by that great and excellent Book, which indeed it is almoſt impoſſible to believe any man could write, but he that was in his Circumſtances and Condition, and under ſuch Thoughts, as ſuch a Condition, when Sanctified, is uſually attended withal.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
